你是巡山队员?
Are you one of the patrol?
对
Yes.
好
Good.
瑞塔的手下?  对
One of Ritai's men? Yeah.
来,把他放了
Fine, then cut him loose.
看什么?不要停
What are you looking at? Don't stop.
把腿抬高
Hold the leg up.
把头转过去一点
Turn the head a bit.
把刀子给我
Give me the knife.
可可西里...
Kekexili...
中国境内最后的原始荒原
the last virgin wilderness of China.
平均海拔四千七百米...
This plain, nearly 4, 700 meters high...
这里是藏羚羊最后的栖息地
is the only remaining habitat of the Tibetan antelope.
1985年以后 盗猎者开始大规模屠杀藏羚羊...
In 1985, poachers began hunting antelopes for their fine wool...
以满足欧美市场对藏羚羊绒的需求
which was prized in foreign markets.
短短几年时间...
Within a few years...
藏羚羊从一百万只锐减至不足一万只
the number of antelopes plunged from one million to under 10,000.
1993年,当地政府组建了一支武装巡山队
A volunteer civilian patrol was formed in 1993 to combat the poachers.
领导人是藏族的领袖瑞塔
It was led by Ritai, a retired Tibetan army officer.
巡山队和盗猎份子发生激战...
The patrol fought fierce battles with the poachers...
引起了海内外媒体的关注
arousing the attention of the outside world.
1996年冬...
In the winter of 1996...
巡山队员在执行任务时被杀害
poachers murdered one of the patrolmen.
报社紧急委派我前来采访
My newspaper immediately sent me to cover the story.
青海
QINGHAI
嘿,先生
Hey, mister.
帮我们照相,早安
Take our picture. Good morning.
瑞塔呢?
Where's Ritai?
瑞塔!
Ritai!
他在那里  谢谢
He's over there. Thanks.
早安
Good morning.
我就是瑞塔
I'm Ritai.
我想采访你
I'd like to interview you.
你是谁?
Who are you?
什么?
What?
介绍信?
Do you have some ID?
我是北京来的记者
I'm a reporter from Beijing.
对不起,我没时间  请等等!
I don't have the time. Wait a second!
听说你正在筹建可可西里自然保护区
You want this place to be declared as a nature reserve.
我是为这件事来的
Maybe I can help.
大瓦  大瓦
Dawa. Dawa.
来了
Yes.
带他上楼
Take him upstairs.
你好,包包给我,跟我走
Your bag. Follow me.
准备晚餐
Prepare dinner.
好
Okay.
你是?  燕晶
You are? Yangjin.
你是瑞塔女儿吧?  是
Are you Ritai's daughter? Yes.
你在看什么?
What are you reading?
没什么,一些资料  哦
Just some documents. Oh.
那您睡吧
Get some rest.
刘栋呢?
Where's Liu Dong?
坐
Sit.
来,吃肉
Here, have some meat.
你切错边了
You're cutting in the wrong direction.
你听得懂藏语?  我爸是藏人
You understand Tibetan? My father's a Tibetan.
我们藏族吃肉,刀口对着自己
Tibetans always point knives towards themselves.
森巴森巴恰恰恰
Samba cha cha cha Samba cha cha cha
龙啊龙啊恰恰恰
Dragon dragon cha cha cha Dragon dragon cha cha cha
你骗人,你输了
You cheat, you lost it.
刘栋,喝
Liu Dong, drink up.
好啦好啦,我喝
Let me drink it for him.
刘栋,走
Liu Dong, let's go.
桑基
Songji.
啥子事啊?你要去哪?  不关你的事
What's wrong? Where are you going? None of your business.
亲爱的,你哪里去?
Honey, where are you going?
刘栋
Liu Dong.
刘栋  好
Liu Dong. Yes.
帮我
Give me a hand.
拿枪
Take your guns.
帮我  好
Give me a hand. Okay.
今晚上我们进山,上车
We're going to the mountains. Hop in.
平安回来!
Come back alive!
照顾自己
Take care of yourself.
1996年,11月1日午夜
MIDNIGHT OF NOVEMBER 1st, 1996
来车了
Here comes a truck.
我们每次进山,都要在这里设卡
We have a checkpoint here.
这里有盗猎份子吗?  不一定
Are there any poachers here? Maybe.
这里离藏羚羊狩猎区最近
We're close to the antelope breeding grounds.
他们经常在此经过
They always pass by here.
你从那里来的?  伍道梁工地
Where are you coming from? Wudaoliang construction site.
到哪儿去?  格尔木
Where are you going? Ge'ermu.
我们是巡山队的
We're the mountain patrol.
要对你进行检查,下车
We need to check your cargo. Get out.
有没有带皮子?  没有
Do you have pelts with you? No.
这什么?  棉花
What are those? It's cotton.
再说一遍,这什么?
Once more, what is this?
这是藏羊绒,走!
It's antelope wool. Move over!
下车
Get off.
怎么处理他?
What will you do with him?
放了呗
Let him go.
这个路上...
He's just a carrier.
帮盗猎份子带藏羚羊绒的人太多了
We don't have the power to arrest anybody...
我们只能没收,没权利抓人
just to confiscate the pelts.
第二天:布东温泉保护站
DAY 2: BUDONG SPRINGS CONSERVATION STATION
阿旺,他是北京来的记者  嗨
A-Wang, he's a reporter from Beijing. Hi.
他会让你出名的!
He'll make you a big star!
好耶!
All right!
来,来,坐
Have a seat.
这是这个月的配给  好,放到角落去
Here are the supplies for this month. Great. Put them in the corner.
阿旺,晚餐快一点  好
A-Wang, hurry up with dinner. Okay.
我的收音机坏了,有什么新闻?
My radio is broken. What's the latest news?
擎巴不跟我们一起了
Qiangba's not with us anymore.
看上另一个女的了?
Chasing after another girl?
他被杀了
He was killed.
你小心点
You be careful.
我把这首歌献给白神殿
I give this song to the White Temple.
我为白神殿高歌
I sing this song for the White Temple.
我把这首歌献给白神殿
I give this song to the White Temple.
我为白神殿高歌
I sing this song for the White Temple.
我把这首歌献给白神殿
I give this song to the White Temple.
我为白神殿高歌
I sing this song for the White Temple.
保重,小心点!再见!
Bless you. Be careful! See you!
保重!
Bless you!
就他一个人?
He's been stationed there all by himself?
都三年了,阿旺在,盗猎者都不敢过来
Yes, he's been there for three years. He keeps the poachers away.
一个人住三年
Three years.
确实没办法,我们人不够
We're short of hands. We haven't enough men to do it.
第三天:周奈湖
DAY 3: ZHUONAI LAKE
403、404、405...
403, 404, 405...
都是藏羚羊吗?
Are they all Tibetan antelopes?
浑蛋
Bastards.
你!过来!
You! Come here!
从哪里来?  绥化
Where are you from? Suihua.
到这里做什么?  找虫
What are you doing here? Collecting worms.
打羊子的见着没有?
Seen any poachers?
见了
Yes.
几个人?
How many?
不知道
I don't know.
你见了?  见了
What about you? I saw some.
几个?
How many?
不知道  不要骗我们!
Don't know. Don't lie to us!
他们一开枪我们就把眼睛闭起来
We closed our eyes when they started shooting.
天太黑了,我们啥都没看到
It was too dark, we saw nothing.
你们有捕猎证吗?
Do you have a fishing permit?
没有
No.
罚款
Fine them.
每年我们进山,都要埋葬一万头藏羚羊
We bury more than 10,000 antelopes each year.
第五天:犁牛沟
DAY 5: YAK VALLEY
没油
No gas.
就是他们
It's them.
刚过去,不超过半里
They were here not long ago.
上车
Let's go.
第七天:库玛河
DAY 7: CUMAR RIVER
那边有人,就是他们!
That's them. Over there!
站住,通通站住!
Stop. All of you!
不要动,全部!
Don't move, all of you!
不要跑!
Hold it there!
趴下!
Get down on the ground!
脱裤子,过河
Take off your pants. Cross the river.
不要跑!
Don't move!
趴下
Down on the ground.
全部
All of you.
局长,没皮子没枪
Captain, they don't have pelts or guns.
趴下
Down on the ground.
伤在哪儿?
Where's he injured?
他的腿
His leg.
没救了
There's no hope.
打在动脉上
It's the artery.
我不要死!
I don't want to die.
你叫什么名字?
What's your name?
马卢
Ma Rui.
哪里来的?
Where are you from?
华隆
Hualong.
多大啦?
How old are you?
二一
Twenty.
你打过羊子吧?
Have you ever killed any antelopes?
帮帮我
Please help me.
(藏族祈祷)
(Tibetan prayer)
带他们过河吧
Take them across the river.
快,蹲下!
Hurry. Kneel down!
马哲立,你这次怎么说?
Ma Zhanlin, do you have anything to say this time?
再给我一件大衣,我冷得受不了
Let me have another coat. I'm freezing cold.
你们家老板呢?
Where's your boss?
我们刚拔了皮子  你给我老实讲
We just skin them. Don't lie.
我就是这样
That's all I do.
别耍花招  我不知道
Tell us the truth. I don't know anything.
你是枪手?  不是
Are you the gunman? No.
你是枪手?  我不是枪手
You're the gunman? No, I'm not.
干啥的?  我是司机
Then what do you do? I'm the driver.
谁是枪手?  我不知道
Who's the gunman? I don't know.
谁知道?  我儿子不是枪手
Who knows? My son is not the gunman.
谁是枪手?  我也不知道
Who is the gunman? I really don't know.
谁知道?
Who knows?
他知道,他请我们来的  马哲立,别胡说!
He knew. He hired us. Ma Zhanlin, cut the crap!
我是这班车司机
I'm just a driver.
你是枪手?  不是枪手,我是这班车司机
Are you the gunman? No, I'm the driver.
那你老实说,谁是枪手  我不知道,他们从没跟我讲
Then tell us who the gunman is. I don't know. They're lying.
我没有办法说  别人说你知道,你知不知道
I really don't know. They say you're in charge.
我不知道,他们出卖我的嘛
They're lying to save themselves.
你是司机,那你为啥不走?
Why are you still here if you're the driver?
车坏掉,我没办法修嘛
The truck broke down. I couldn't fix it.
他们看不见你了,说吧
They can't see you now. Talk.
看不见也没有办法呀
I really don't know anything.
这是你的最后机会  真的没办法嘛
This is your last chance. I really can't help.
说!  我什么都不知道
Talk! I don't know anything.
说!  我真的不知道,我是司机嘛
Talk! I know nothing. I just drive the truck.
我不知道,真的不知道  说!
I don't know. I really don't. Talk to us!
我什么都不知道
I don't know anything.
说
Talk.
我真的不知道  说不说
I know nothing. Talk to us.
放我走  说不说
Let me go. Talk to us.
再不说就打死你!
Talk now or I'll shoot you!
我真的不知道
I don't know anything.
再不说就打死你!
Talk now or I'll shoot you!
好,不要打死我,我说我说
All right, I'll tell you. Don't kill me.
皮子在这里
The pelts are here.
挖
Dig.
都在这里,底下还有
They're all here. There are more underneath.
有几张皮子?
How many do we have?
五百四十七张,大多数是母羊  现在是交配季节
547, mostly female. It's the breeding season.
真可惜
What a shame.
枪手跑了
The gunman got away.
刚才抓的人呢?
What about the men you captured?
这些都是小口径
They were from small caliber rifles.
这些羊子都是冲锋枪打的
The real gunmen use machine guns.
我追了他们好多年
I've been chasing them for years.
给我根烟好吗?
Can I have one?
我也好几天没抽烟了
I haven't smoked for several days, too.
谢谢
Thanks.
大爷,您干什么的?
What do you do?
我剥皮子的
I skin the animals.
剥一张皮子给您多少钱?
How much do they pay you?
五块钱
Five Yuan for each pelt.
我在格尔木是剥皮子最快、最便宜的人
I'm the fastest skinner in Ge'ermu.
全家都在这里
All my children are here, too.
他是老大,他是老二,这是老么
He's my eldest, here's the middle one, and the youngest.
他们都在剥皮子
They're all skinners.
我以前是放羊的
In the past, I was a shepherd.
放羊、放牛、放骆驼
I herded sheep, cattle, and camels.
现在这个村变荒原
Now the grasslands have turned into desert.
牛和羊死的死了,卖的卖了
The sheep and cattle all gone dead or sold off.
人也没得吃的,人也活不下去
It's tough to survive here.
我要上一号(指厕所)  我也是
I need to pee. Me, too.
好,不要叫了
All right, stop yelling.
葛玉,把篮子给我
Gayu, hand me the bucket.
我要撒尿  等一下
I want to pee. Wait your turn.
枪手往北面走,他们肯定要过这条河
The gunmen had to cross this river, if they're heading north.
可以过!
It's crossable!
1、2、3!
One, two, three!
起来帮忙
Get up and help.
谁要喝一杯?
Who wants a drink?
第九天
DAY 9
绳子
Rope.
一人半个
Everyone gets a half.
多给点吧?我好几天没吃东西了
I want more. I haven't eaten anything in days.
我告诉你,没你吃的 是我们省下来的,知道不知道
We are sharing our food with you. That's all you get.
谢谢你啊
Thank you.
像流动的水
Like flowing water
哦,亲爱的妈
Oh, dear mother
不管我去多远
No matter how far I travel
我会回来 不管我去多远
I shall return no matter how far I travel
美丽的白云 请帮我传信
Clouds of brilliant white please deliver my message
我想家
I long for home
我在心中为你祈祷
I pray for you in my heart
进去
Get inside.
转过来
Turn around.
没睡啊?
Can't sleep?
这一区不舒服,在车外站站就行
The air's thin up here. It's better outside the car.
又流鼻血了  没事
Your nose is bleeding again. It's all right.
真漂亮  就是
It's beautiful. It is.
说老实话,每次巡山到最后 发疯地想回去
I get homesick every time I go out on patrol.
见到公路上的灯就像见到家里
Even the lights on the highway remind me of home.
可是回去两、三天 又想到可可西里
But when I'm home I start thinking of Kekexili.
你觉得可可西里是什么意思?
Do you know what Kekexili means in Tibetan?
可可西里在我们藏语中是 “美丽的青山、美丽的少女”
It means "Beautiful mountains and girls."
就是,在可可西里...
That isn't it. In Kekexili...
你踩下的每个脚印...
each step may be the first human footprint...
有可能是地球诞生以来 人类留下的第一个脚印
ever made on that spot since the world began.
这句话不是我说的
Those aren't my words.
两年前,从北京来的一个地质学家
Two years ago, a geologist came from Beijing.
我送他进可可西里,是他跟我讲的
I took him to Kekexili and he said that to me.
后来那个地质学家在可可西里失踪了
Later the geologist went missing.
到现在都没有找到
No one has seen him since.
这里到处都是吃人的流沙
There's a lot of quicksand around here.
你白痴!
You idiot!
盗猎者呢?
Where are the poachers?
他们人呢?
Where are they?
马哲立带他三个儿子跑了  啥时候睡着的?
Ma Zhanlin escaped with his sons. When did you fall asleep?
大概五点多钟
Around 5:00 a.m.
队长!
Captain!
滚开!
Let go of me!
追!
Hunt them down!
站住!
Stop!
站住!听到了没?
Stop! Did you hear me?
蹲下!
Get down! Down!
看着他!
Watch him!
起来!
Get up!
钥匙呢?
Where's the key?
我没带
I don't have it.
我确实没带
I really don't have it.
这是什么?
What's this?
他怎么啦?
What's wrong?
肺气肿
Pulmonary edema.
水?
Water?
没水了
There isn't any.
让我试一下呗
I can help.
就让他试一下吧 他过去在格尔木当过兽医
Let him try, he was a vet in Ge'ermu.
捏住他的手臂
Hold his arm.
刘栋,带大瓦回去看医生
Liu Dong, you take Dawa back to see the doctor.
平丘,你也该回去
Ping Cuo, you should go back, too.
我的肩伤没那么糟
My shoulder wound isn't that bad.
我可以帮忙看犯人
I can help watch the prisoners.
好
All right.
我们要钱看医生
We need money for the doctor.
拿钱
Give him some money.
不够
It's not enough.
还有吗?  这是县里的罚款?
Do we have more? Only the fine for the country.
给他
Give it to him.
不够
It's still not enough.
卖皮子
Sell the pelts.
我去追他们
I'm going after the gunman.
走花圆沟进来
You take the route through Huatugou.
好
Okay.
保重  保重
Good luck. Good luck.
再见  再见
Goodbye. Goodbye.
保重
Be safe.
再见
Goodbye.
局长,吃的没有了
Captain, we're almost out of food.
能撑多少天?
How much do we have left?
两天,不包括犯人的
Two days worth for us. Not counting the prisoners.
油也不多了,还剩最后一桶 现在回去...
Fuel's nearly gone, too. We should turn back...
回去不可能!
No way!
还能开几天?
How much fuel is there?
三、四天,卡车可能带不上
Four days if we give up the truck.
三、四天应该就成
That should allow us to catch them.
退后
Step back.
把手铐打开
Remove the handcuffs.
马哲立
Ma Zhanlin.
每次我抓到你,你都是罚款
Every time I catch you, you pay a fine.
这次不罚了,让你走
This time I'm letting you go without a fine.
真好走啊?
Really?
嗯,我放你走
Yes.
我走不出去,我老了
I'm too old to make it back from here.
我没粮食给你们吃,油也不多了
I don't have food for you, and I'm short of fuel.
我还要抓你们的老板,我管不了
I'm going after your boss. I can't take care of you.
我走不出去
I can't make it.
马哲立,你走得出去
Yes, you can.
到艾尔山走200多公里
It's 200 kilometers to the Al Mountain.
到昆仑山口100多公里
And 100 more to the Kunlun Pass.
你能走出去
You can make it.
确实走不出去,就是你的命
If you don't make it, then it's your fate.
保重
Good luck.
愿神保佑你
May God be with you.
第十天:布格达班峰
DAY 10: BUGEDABAN PEAK
啥回事?
What's wrong?
引擎坏了
The engine's gone.
油也没了
Out of oil.
出发的时候为什么不检查?
Why didn't you check the oil before?
车子都开两天了
We've been going nonstop for two days.
还能修吗?
Can you fix it?
你们在这儿等刘栋
Wait here for Liu Dong.
我们走
Let's go.
保重
Good luck.
保重!
Good luck!
刘栋能找到他们吗?
Can Liu Dong find them?
但愿不要下雪
If it doesn't snow.
第十二天
DAY 12
第十五天
DAY 15
医生
Doctor.
起来
Get up.
这个长凳是给病人的,你的朋友没事
This bench is for patients. Your friend is all right.
你要干嘛?我还在工作
What do you want? I'm still working.
你去哪里去了这么久?
Where have you been for so long?
你真是一团糟
You're a mess.
我在工作,放手
I'm working. Let go of me.
冷不冷,穿个鱼网?
Aren't you cold in those fishnets?
工作服
It's my working outfit.
你到底要什么?
What do you want from me anyway?
看你这个样子 跟个神经病一样
You look like a lunatic.
不说话装什么聋子
Are you playing deaf now?
我想你!
I miss you!
你想我却不来看我
You miss me but you didn't come to see me.
我巡山去了
I went patrolling.
我以为你死了
I thought you were dead.
我需要点钱
I need some money.
怎么每次来找我都这样!
You pull this shit every time I see you!
李序  你以为我开银行?
Lengxue. Do you think I own a bank?
是不是拿我的钱养其他女人?
Did you spend my money on other women?
我不知道你怎么能过那种生活
I don't know how you can live that crazy life.
我只想跟你在一起
I just want to be with you.
我要走了
I'm leaving.
你很快就把我给忘记了
You'll forget me soon.
再找另一个姑娘跟你在一起
And find yourself another girl.
李序
Lengxue.
马哲立他们能不能活着走出去?
Can Ma Zhanlin make it out alive?
你的人呢?
What about your men?
但愿不要下雪
I hope it doesn't snow.
怎么啦?
What's wrong?
他们没找到我们
They'll never find us.
咱们走不出去了
We're going to die here.
闭嘴!
Shut up!
你们现在最大的困难是什么?
Your whole situation looks pretty desperate.
钱也没有,人也没有,枪也没有
We're short of money, short of men, short of guns.
我的弟兄们一年没拿钱了
My guys haven't been paid for almost a year.
县里不能解决经费问题吗?
Can the country help?
我们没编制
We're not officially employed.
队里的经费是不是特别紧张?
How do you pay for the patrol?
都是我们自己解决
We have to raise the money ourselves.
你们怎么处理缴回来的皮子?
What do you do with the pelts?
大部分都上缴
We hand most of them over to the authorities.
你们会不会也卖一部份皮子来解决经费问题?
Do you sell some to raise the money?
卖皮子是违法的
Selling the pelts is illegal.
你说我该怎么写这篇报导?
How should I write the article?
我一直认为我是个好记者...
I always thought I was a good journalist...
我知道你是记者
I know you're a reporter.
这可可西里 就是你们记者保护得来的吗?
You think Kekexili can be protected by reporters?
我知道会进监狱
I'll go to prison if I have to.
我知道卖皮子是犯法的
I know selling pelts is illegal.
但我现在不会考虑你说的
But I can't worry about that now.
我只考虑可可西里...
I can only think about Kekexili...
考虑我的兄弟
and my brothers.
见过朝圣的人吗?
Ever seen protestors on a pilgrimage?
他们的手和脸脏得很
Their faces and hands are filthy.
可他们的心特别干净
But their hearts are pure.
我卖过皮子
I've sold pelts before.
可我没办法
I had no choice.
翻过雪山就是公路
The highway's on the other side of the mountains.
我们必须在他们上公路之前追上他们
We have to catch them before they get there.
看看四周有没有吃的
Look around for something to eat.
子弹多不多?
How many bullets do we have?
还有几十发
A few dozen.
宜兴以前是做什么的?
Yixi, what did you do before this?
上学
I was a student.
上什么学?  青海师大
Where? Qinghai Normal University.
你应该去做老师
You should be a teacher.
干这工作有意思
This job is more interesting.
葛玉,你结婚没有?
Gayu, are you married?
还没有  有女朋友吗?
No. Girlfriend?
有过,来这之前刚分手
We broke up right before I came here.
没关系...
Just like my patrol...
他们进可可西里,女朋友就跑了
each time they go out, their girlfriends leave them.
好姑娘多得很,再找呗
There are plenty of nice girls out there.
是不是?宜兴
Isn't that right, Yixi?
就是
Right.
巴丁以前是干什么的?
What did Bading do before?
专门打兔子
A professional rabbit hunter.
你才打兔子呢
Nonsense.
巴丁以前在检查站  运送木头
He worked at a highway checkpoint. For logging trucks.
我的队员干什么的都有
They worked in all kinds of jobs before joining the team.
刘栋以前是开计程车的
Liu Dong was a taxi driver.
阿旺当过兵
A-Wang was a soldier.
桑基是游牧者
Songji was a herder.
给你
For you.
吃吧!
Have some!
进雪山就没吃的啦
There's nothing to eat up in those mountains.
第十七天
DAY 17
他们能不能从山里走出来?
Can Yixi and Bading find their way out?
没问题
I think so.
要不要在这里等他们?
Should we wait for them here?
马哲立,你活着出来啦
Ma Zhanlin, you're still alive.
就是,雪山里死了好多人
I am. But many died on the way out.
我的队员也在雪山走散了
My team got separated, too.
他是瑞塔队长
This is Capt. Ritai.
这是我们老板
This is our boss.
队长,抽根烟吧
Captain, have a smoke.
我抓了你好几年
I've been chasing you for years.
为什么?
Why?
你打了我的羊子
You killed my antelope.
现在打羊子的人多啊  我不管
So did a lot of people. That's no excuse.
你想怎么样?
So what do you want?
你跟我走
You to come with me.
队长,如果你放了我...
Captain, if you let me off the hook...
我买两辆车给你...
I'll buy you two cars...
再帮你该一个新家
and I'll build you a new house, too.
我老板好心,又有钱...  闭嘴!
Our boss is kind, and he's rich... Shut up!
把枪交上,人跟我走
Surrender your guns and come with me.
那好!那好!把枪交给队长
Sure! Let's give the Captain our guns.
我们当巡山队员去
We'll join his mountain patrol.
谁开的枪?
Who fired?
Who fired the gun?
谁?  我
Who? I did.
浑蛋,你差点打到我
Fuck you. You almost hit me.
他还活着
He's still alive.
你是巡山员吗?
Are you a patrolman?
不是,他不是瑞塔的人
No, he's not Ritai's guy.
如果是就没命啦!
You're a dead man if you are!
他不是!
He's not.
跟着我们的脚印走五公里就到公路了
Follow our footprints for five kilometers to get to the highway.
葛玉回到北京 写出了让世界震撼的报导
四名队员因参与贩卖藏羚羊皮被逮捕
但随后被免予刑事起诉
一年后,中国政府在可可西里 设立国家自然保护区
并成立森林公安机关
原志愿巡山队自此解散
目前大部分国家 已立法禁止藏羚羊绒贩卖
可可西里的藏羚羊已回升至三万余只
影片源于可可西里巡山队的真实故事